<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Small HQ Blog</title>
  <id>http://www.smallhq.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://www.smallhq.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://www.smallhq.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-02-19T08:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    <name>Joelle Steiniger</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Your Startup is Overthinking Design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.smallhq.com/blog/your-startup-is-overthinking-design/"/>
    <id>http://www.smallhq.com/blog/your-startup-is-overthinking-design/</id>
    <published>2014-02-19T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-19T09:29:45-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Your Startup is Overthinking Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Design matters. A great deal. But design doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;It certainly shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be the thing preventing your startup from starting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I come from an agency background where design was completed first, then on to development, then quality assurance, and finally hand-off. Project finished. Woohoo!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The blessing (and curse) of working with software is that it&amp;rsquo;s never finished. Small changes happen daily, and major overhauls happen monthly. Until you find product-market fit, you&amp;rsquo;re essentially a chicken running around with your head cut off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So why on earth would you spend a bunch of cash on day 1 hiring a designer to design every screen in your dream app? You know it&amp;rsquo;s all going to be worthless within a couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The reality is&amp;hellip;most of you don&amp;rsquo;t pay for good design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It&amp;rsquo;s why tons of developer-led projects look awful, or end up using &lt;a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/"&gt;Foundation&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; to have a &lt;em&gt;decent-looking&lt;/em&gt; app.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not all about looks, you know.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s about having a distinct brand that people recognize from a mile away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We think we&amp;rsquo;ve found a better way&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  How We Handle Design at Small HQ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Neither Joelle nor I are designers, but we have a big following of designers, which leads me to believe that our products don&amp;rsquo;t look too shabby :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We stumbled upon a process, due to our attempts to avoid high costs early-on, that has worked amazing so far &lt;em&gt;(and that we&amp;rsquo;ve replicated several times since)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Whenever starting a new product, we hire a designer. But we don&amp;rsquo;t hire them to design the whole product&amp;hellip;just a style guide for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  A Photoshop file that includes a color palette, typography options for different use cases, button styles, form fields, and a simple logotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The cost of this deliverable is typically in the hundreds &lt;em&gt;(not the thousands) &lt;/em&gt;and any developer you work with should be able to execute your product according to the style guide&lt;em&gt; (if not - look for a new developer)&lt;/em&gt;. Here are the early style guides for &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;HookFeed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;Minimalytics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/hf-styles.gif" style="border:2px solid #5A9BCE;width:566px;margin-left:0px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/smallhq/mnml-styles.gif" style="border:2px solid #5A9BCE;width:566px;margin-left:0px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We love amazing design. And we want everything we produce to look good &amp;ndash; especially since our customers are often designers. But design matters no matter who your audience is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;People judge your product in a split-second. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it needs bells and whistles, or screenshots of your app, or illustrations, or anything else really. But it needs to be clean, have legible typography, and look like it wasn&amp;rsquo;t thrown together by a newbie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you aren&amp;rsquo;t willing to put effort into the single page advertising your product&amp;hellip;how can your customers possibly believe you&amp;rsquo;ve given the product any polish, design- or functionality-wise. &lt;strong&gt;And forget about anyone giving you their credit card!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But regardless of how important design is&amp;hellip;it&amp;rsquo;s simply not rational to spend thousands, or even a small equity stake on upfront product design when you have no clue what your product will look like 6 months from now. Hell, even 1 month from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So put down Bootstrap, discard your awful line-heights and font-sizing, and fork over a few hundred to solidify your product&amp;rsquo;s brand, without paying for the extras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  Finding the Perfect Designer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Here are a few quick tips to ensure things run smoothly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Check &lt;a href="http://www.dribbble.com"&gt;Dribbble&lt;/a&gt; regularly, and &amp;ldquo;like&amp;rdquo; the shots that make you drool. &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/benchwarmer-dribbble-for/lhdjhhpjicomphhjpehdhjenbaamdpnn?hl=en"&gt;Benchwarmer&lt;/a&gt; is awesome for this&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Over time, you&amp;rsquo;ll build up a collection of &amp;ldquo;liked&amp;rdquo; work that you can show to any designer to give them a concrete idea of the style you like. &lt;a href="http://dribbble.com/SDMattG/shots/likes"&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s mine&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    When ready, look at the designers&amp;#39; whose work you&amp;rsquo;re constantly liking, and click the Hire Me button on their Dribbble profiles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Write a detailed email to each describing your project (get them excited!) and link them to your Dribbble &amp;ldquo;likes&amp;rdquo; page. Describe exactly what you need (i.e. blog typography styles, logotype, 2 primary colors, 5 secondary colors, button styles, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you do it all right, you&amp;rsquo;ve just given a few &lt;em&gt;(hopefully)&lt;/em&gt; pumped designers a well-defined scope/budget/direction for a brief project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;And the best part is, it won&amp;rsquo;t slow down product development. &lt;/strong&gt;While the style guide is being created, you can be focused on building the ugly version of your product, which you can later style to match the guide.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Road to SaaS Revenue is Painfully Slow. Are You Prepared for It?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.smallhq.com/blog/the-road-to-saas-revenue-is-painfully-slow-are-you-prepared-for-it/"/>
    <id>http://www.smallhq.com/blog/the-road-to-saas-revenue-is-painfully-slow-are-you-prepared-for-it/</id>
    <published>2014-02-12T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-12T10:03:29-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Road to SaaS Revenue is Painfully Slow. Are You Prepared for It?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;ve heard of successful SaaS products like &lt;a href="http://basecamp.com"&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://letsfreckle.com"&gt;Freckle&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://bidsketch.com"&gt;Bidsketch&lt;/a&gt;. These were the companies that inspired us personally to go down the SaaS route. If they could do it, so could we&amp;hellip;right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I wish it were that simple! Building a &lt;strong&gt;bootstrapped&lt;/strong&gt; SaaS business is really, really, really frickin&amp;#39; hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  You can have popular blog posts, a huge list of prospects, a successful beta, and even launch into revenue/profit. But without revenue streams besides your SaaS, you will&amp;nbsp;likely fail in the first year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  That&amp;rsquo;s right, your self-funded venture will fail if you don&amp;rsquo;t do one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell a product/productized service (book, course, membership site, webinar, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell your time (consulting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell your time (part- or full-time job)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Most SaaS founders don&amp;rsquo;t talk about this reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But &lt;strong&gt;a huge majority of the founders&lt;/strong&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ve talked to so far (&lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com/podcast"&gt;on the podcast&lt;/a&gt;) spend their first few months/years making their money from sources besides their SaaS product. And many of them continue offering high-end services far after their SaaS becomes &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Don&amp;rsquo;t believe me? We&amp;rsquo;ve heard it first-hand from entrepreneurs like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brennandunn"&gt;Brennan Dunn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/toddo"&gt;Todd Garland&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drewwilson"&gt;Drew Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/earthlingworks"&gt;Ruben Gamez&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It&amp;rsquo;s not fun or sexy to think about these sorts of things when you&amp;rsquo;d much rather be spending your time working on your baby: that one thing that brings you closer to full freedom than you&amp;rsquo;ve ever been.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But the sooner you embrace this &lt;em&gt;(we waited way too long),&lt;/em&gt; the longer your runway will be and the less stress you&amp;rsquo;ll inflict on yourself and those around you. So let&amp;rsquo;s get down to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  0. Don&amp;rsquo;t Turn Down (Good) Consulting Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We&amp;rsquo;ve avoided consulting work like the plague. And it&amp;rsquo;s been great&amp;hellip;it&amp;rsquo;s allowed us to push our products forward at a great rate. But even at a great rate, SaaS revenue takes a long time to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Absolutely turn down long-term contract projects that would distract you or your team. But think twice before rejecting/not pursuing retainer work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I highly recommend &lt;a href="http://doubleyourfreelancingrate.com/"&gt;Brennan&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;. It convinced us to charge 5x our normal rate on the only contract we&amp;rsquo;ve taken since we started. His advice also helped us extend that job into a monthly retainer which is locked in for 12 months now, giving us some level of stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  1. Market Your Product before You Build It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Before you start building your product, put up a simple, yet descriptive, page selling the dream (&lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s one of ours&lt;/a&gt;). Don&amp;rsquo;t use LaunchRock, and don&amp;rsquo;t skimp on design. If you&amp;rsquo;re truly keeping it simple, you should be able to find a great designer on Dribbble that will produce a style guide to keep you on track. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but when I see a half-assed landing page, I assume the eventual product won&amp;rsquo;t have any polish/effort invested either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This page is your calling card. Anyone you interact with on Twitter or in Email will be viewing your product&amp;rsquo;s page and judging your competency as a maker. All of your future outreach/reputation as an entrepreneur depend on this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  2. Use this Marketing to Build a Personal Newsletter that Attracts Your Audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We&amp;rsquo;ve been operating for nearly a year, and this is the first time we&amp;rsquo;ve sat down and thought about what we could send of value to the folks that have signed up for the Small HQ list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  All of our prior focus has been on growing beta lists, and upon realizing how slow SaaS is, we&amp;rsquo;re now making an attempt to grow the company outside of the SaaS.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  What can you do to provide value to your audience on a regular basis, regardless of whether or not it supports your SaaS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  3. Sell an eBook or other Non-SaaS Product to this Audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We started promoting our book about 6-9 months ago. Then it sat there, ignored. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michaelsacca"&gt;Michael Sacca&lt;/a&gt; approached us about partnering up on a broader book that we got our asses in gear. Since then, we&amp;rsquo;ve started publishing our &lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com/podcast"&gt;founder interviews&lt;/a&gt;, and have many more plans for the &lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com"&gt;Rocketship&lt;/a&gt; brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We should have been doing all of this work last summer, but instead we were focused on building (and then rebuilding) our &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;SaaS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Don&amp;rsquo;t make the same mistake. Sell your knowledge, and give a lot away for free. Let that momentum fuel your product development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  4. Build Your Product along the Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you do everything right, you should have some side-revenue coming in from 1 or more non-SaaS products. More importantly, you will have built up relationships which can be turned into partnerships on other products/services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It took us a very long time to realize what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t, and we&amp;rsquo;ve continued to be fairly non-deliberate in our actions. Moving forward, we&amp;rsquo;re trying to be more strategic about where we spend our energy. Focusing most on revenue-driving activities, and less on distracting side-projects/our SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="font-size:14px;"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The end of 2013 marks roughly the three-year mark for my company. As I reflect on where we are today, from initial product, to an advisory round, to seed funding and then to raising our Series A in December 2013, one thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve always perceived came true: &lt;strong&gt;it takes roughly 3 years for you to truly figure out if what you&amp;rsquo;re working on can be a business.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style="font-size:14px;"&gt;&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Tawheed"&gt;Tawheed Kader&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www1.toutapp.com/"&gt;Tout App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
