<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Small HQ Blog</title>
  <id>http://www.smallhq.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://www.smallhq.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://www.smallhq.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-02-12T08:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    <name>Joelle Steiniger</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Road to SaaS Revenue is Painfully Slow. Are You Prepared for It?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.smallhq.com/blog/the-road-to-saas-revenue-is-painfully-slow-are-you-prepared-for-it/"/>
    <id>http://www.smallhq.com/blog/the-road-to-saas-revenue-is-painfully-slow-are-you-prepared-for-it/</id>
    <published>2014-02-12T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-12T10:03:29-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Matt Goldman</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Road to SaaS Revenue is Painfully Slow. Are You Prepared for It?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;ve heard of successful SaaS products like &lt;a href="http://basecamp.com"&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://letsfreckle.com"&gt;Freckle&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://bidsketch.com"&gt;Bidsketch&lt;/a&gt;. These were the companies that inspired us personally to go down the SaaS route. If they could do it, so could we&amp;hellip;right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I wish it were that simple! Building a &lt;strong&gt;bootstrapped&lt;/strong&gt; SaaS business is really, really, really frickin&amp;#39; hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  You can have popular blog posts, a huge list of prospects, a successful beta, and even launch into revenue/profit. But without revenue streams besides your SaaS, you will&amp;nbsp;likely fail in the first year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  That&amp;rsquo;s right, your self-funded venture will fail if you don&amp;rsquo;t do one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell a product/productized service (book, course, membership site, webinar, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell your time (consulting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    Sell your time (part- or full-time job)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Most SaaS founders don&amp;rsquo;t talk about this reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But &lt;strong&gt;a huge majority of the founders&lt;/strong&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ve talked to so far (&lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com/podcast"&gt;on the podcast&lt;/a&gt;) spend their first few months/years making their money from sources besides their SaaS product. And many of them continue offering high-end services far after their SaaS becomes &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Don&amp;rsquo;t believe me? We&amp;rsquo;ve heard it first-hand from entrepreneurs like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brennandunn"&gt;Brennan Dunn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/toddo"&gt;Todd Garland&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drewwilson"&gt;Drew Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/earthlingworks"&gt;Ruben Gamez&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It&amp;rsquo;s not fun or sexy to think about these sorts of things when you&amp;rsquo;d much rather be spending your time working on your baby: that one thing that brings you closer to full freedom than you&amp;rsquo;ve ever been.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But the sooner you embrace this &lt;em&gt;(we waited way too long),&lt;/em&gt; the longer your runway will be and the less stress you&amp;rsquo;ll inflict on yourself and those around you. So let&amp;rsquo;s get down to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  0. Don&amp;rsquo;t Turn Down (Good) Consulting Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We&amp;rsquo;ve avoided consulting work like the plague. And it&amp;rsquo;s been great&amp;hellip;it&amp;rsquo;s allowed us to push our products forward at a great rate. But even at a great rate, SaaS revenue takes a long time to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Absolutely turn down long-term contract projects that would distract you or your team. But think twice before rejecting/not pursuing retainer work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I highly recommend &lt;a href="http://doubleyourfreelancingrate.com/"&gt;Brennan&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;. It convinced us to charge 5x our normal rate on the only contract we&amp;rsquo;ve taken since we started. His advice also helped us extend that job into a monthly retainer which is locked in for 12 months now, giving us some level of stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  1. Market Your Product before You Build It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Before you start building your product, put up a simple, yet descriptive, page selling the dream (&lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s one of ours&lt;/a&gt;). Don&amp;rsquo;t use LaunchRock, and don&amp;rsquo;t skimp on design. If you&amp;rsquo;re truly keeping it simple, you should be able to find a great designer on Dribbble that will produce a style guide to keep you on track. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but when I see a half-assed landing page, I assume the eventual product won&amp;rsquo;t have any polish/effort invested either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This page is your calling card. Anyone you interact with on Twitter or in Email will be viewing your product&amp;rsquo;s page and judging your competency as a maker. All of your future outreach/reputation as an entrepreneur depend on this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  2. Use this Marketing to Build a Personal Newsletter that Attracts Your Audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We&amp;rsquo;ve been operating for nearly a year, and this is the first time we&amp;rsquo;ve sat down and thought about what we could send of value to the folks that have signed up for the Small HQ list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  All of our prior focus has been on growing beta lists, and upon realizing how slow SaaS is, we&amp;rsquo;re now making an attempt to grow the company outside of the SaaS.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  What can you do to provide value to your audience on a regular basis, regardless of whether or not it supports your SaaS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  3. Sell an eBook or other Non-SaaS Product to this Audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We started promoting our book about 6-9 months ago. Then it sat there, ignored. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michaelsacca"&gt;Michael Sacca&lt;/a&gt; approached us about partnering up on a broader book that we got our asses in gear. Since then, we&amp;rsquo;ve started publishing our &lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com/podcast"&gt;founder interviews&lt;/a&gt;, and have many more plans for the &lt;a href="http://howtobuildarocketship.com"&gt;Rocketship&lt;/a&gt; brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We should have been doing all of this work last summer, but instead we were focused on building (and then rebuilding) our &lt;a href="http://www.hookfeed.com"&gt;SaaS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.minimalytics.com"&gt;products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Don&amp;rsquo;t make the same mistake. Sell your knowledge, and give a lot away for free. Let that momentum fuel your product development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;
  4. Build Your Product along the Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you do everything right, you should have some side-revenue coming in from 1 or more non-SaaS products. More importantly, you will have built up relationships which can be turned into partnerships on other products/services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It took us a very long time to realize what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t, and we&amp;rsquo;ve continued to be fairly non-deliberate in our actions. Moving forward, we&amp;rsquo;re trying to be more strategic about where we spend our energy. Focusing most on revenue-driving activities, and less on distracting side-projects/our SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="font-size:14px;"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The end of 2013 marks roughly the three-year mark for my company. As I reflect on where we are today, from initial product, to an advisory round, to seed funding and then to raising our Series A in December 2013, one thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve always perceived came true: &lt;strong&gt;it takes roughly 3 years for you to truly figure out if what you&amp;rsquo;re working on can be a business.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span style="font-size:14px;"&gt;&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Tawheed"&gt;Tawheed Kader&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www1.toutapp.com/"&gt;Tout App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
